<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veenaramesh.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veenaramesh.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-14T21:58:16+00:00</updated><id>https://veenaramesh.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Veena Ramesh</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Avatar the Last Airbender (Live Action)</title><link href="https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2023/atla-live-action/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Avatar the Last Airbender (Live Action)"/><published>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2023/atla-live-action</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2023/atla-live-action/"><![CDATA[<p>Warning: This post may contain spoilers about the live action Avatar the Last Airbender as well as the animated show.</p> <p>The resurgence and Avatar the Last Airbender (ATLA) over the last few years has been astonishing, especially as a long time fan of the show. The show has widely been regarded as one of the best animated shows of all time; the fight choreography, the animation style, the intensity of the characters all stood out, especially in the early 2000s (think Chowder, Spongebob as the standouts of children’s programming). I remember it as being one of the shows with an actual storyline, and I still remember it to this day as something that shaped my philosophical understanding.</p> <p>Recently, the live action ATLA was released on Netflix to a lot less praise. The art direction was flaws, the acting was bed, and the storyline was dumbed down for what I assume to be an audience of millenials. It was a disappointing return to the world, but it was an unsurprising one. Despite the amount of live action adaptations of animated shows, there have been only a few that have truly lived up to the drama and beauty of the original. Animation as a medium has a great knack for being disrespected despite its intrinsic way of weaving magic and genuinity to a story.</p> <p>Even beyond this, the live action show was just horrible. The adaptation changed not only the medium but changed essential narrative traits of the show as well, making the characters and themes of the show weaker.</p> <h4 id="aang-and-zuko">Aang and Zuko</h4> <p>The live action show opens up dramatically differently than the animated show. We are in the world of Sozin, and Aang dramatically leaves Monk Gyatso and the Southern Air Temple, fearing his own responsibilities as the Avatar. Aang’s original backstory is actually first properly introduced in season 1, episode 12 “The Storm.” It is the episode that ultimately frames the next few seasons as it is sets Zuko and Aang as foils of each other.</p> <p>In “The Storm”, Aang tells Katara why he was stuck in the iceberg and Uncle Iroh explans why Zuko is searching for the Avatar. The story is quite simple. But this sets up Zuko and Aang as foils of each other. And because we frame the characters against each other in this way, we (as the observor) can inform ourselves about Aang’s fears through our understanding of Zuko and about Zuko’s moral complexities through our understanding of Aang. The juxtaposition of Zuko’s character against Aang gives us way more insight to both characters without having to recite each character’s traits verbatim.</p> <p>These literary tricks are lost in the new live action adaptation. Instead the live action show relies on the observor to have already watched and understood the original show. It does none of the fundamental work to make you care for any of these characters.</p> <p>Another huge misstep that frustrated me was the treatment of the genocide of the Airbenders as a plot point. While, yes, it was an incredibly important event within the world of Avatar, the show treats it as just that; Aang as a character seems so distant from it all as if he has no relationship with the airbenders. Aang being an airbender is so incredibly important to the story! It is the largest internal conflict in the first season and the last few episodes (“will Aang kill Ozai?”) The live action drained all of the complications of Aang’s character by recontextualizing many of the plot points.</p> <h4 id="azula">Azula</h4> <p>Azula is my favorite antagonist of all time. She is such a fun character, and she was so different from every other kind of antagonist at the time. She was fourteeen! She was a prodigy! Her father loved her! She has no moral compass! How fun! Her introduction was so jarring that even though Zuko is framed as an antagonist well into season 3, Azula is clearly quite different.</p> <p>Her fall from perfection is heavily foreshadowed and almost expected, but we only get insight into her psyche in that last episode during the Last Agni Kai.</p> <p>In this new version of ATLA, Ozai’s abuse of Azula is not only more obvious but it is completely different. Something that stuck with me in the original show is what Zuko says to Aang (Aang is not conscious) in the season 1 finale: “My father said she was born lucky. He said I was luck to be born.” Ozai’s emotional and physical abuse of Zuko is completely different from the manipulation faced by Azula, who is more tortured by the ‘what if’ of it all. What would happen if she failed like Zuko? In the live action show, instead Ozai emotionally manipulates her in the same way that he manipulates Zuko, which changes her dynamic with Zuko and Ozai. Sanitizing Azula’s psyche makes her behavior more confusing and less interesting.</p> <p>A smaller character point that is brought up repeatedly in the show is the idea of a prodigy vs someone who is diligent in their practice (e.g. Aang automatically understanding how to waterbend vs Katara practicing in secret to perfect her skills, Azula naturally able to bend lightning vs Zuko still perfecting his basics to achieve peace). The idea is that those who practice regularly and diligently will always outperform those who are just naturally gifted (and the underlying assumption here is that the prodigy does not practice their skills in as diligent of a manner). Azula’s interest in defeating Zuko is not because Ozai has pitted them against each other; in flashbacks and even in their ongoing fight scenes, it is clear that Azula does not respect Zuko as a firebender and her drive to destroying him is rooted in that. The live action show now changing how Ozai and Azula interact would cut off Azula’s own justification of chasing and killing Zuko. Azula (a clear prodigy) would obviously have no interest in competing with Zuko for her father’s attention– she already has it.</p> <h4 id="katara">Katara</h4> <p>I do not have much to say about Katara as she was the most obviously butchered character in the live action. There was this rumor about removing the more ‘dated’ (i.e. sexist) aspects of show in order to make a more empowering character. However, by doing so, they reinforced a lot of incredibly sexist traits. Katara has no personality in the show. She has no drive, no complex relationship with her brother, no real interest in bending, or any anger. This attempt to remove these ‘sexist’ traits have ultimately stripped her of any personality and depth.</p> <p>I realize that the show is not interested in the exploration of these characters. They start as static characters, and they will end up the same. Katara’s anger, Aang’s childishness, Azula’s antagonism– these are all necessary to shape and understand the world that ATLA takes place in. Removing any of these perceived ‘negative’ traits to create more relatable characters (for us the viewers) actually does the exact opposite.</p> <p>Anyways, don’t watch the show. It is bad.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="bad"/><category term="essays"/><category term="media,"/><category term="opinion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Warning: This post may contain spoilers about the live action Avatar the Last Airbender as well as the animated show.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veenaramesh.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>